Finding Aid for Benjamin F. Graves papers, 1815-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Benjamin F. Graves papers 1815-1950, 1848-1903
Graves, Benjamin Franklin, b. 1817.
2.5 linear feet
85709 Aa 2
Circuit court judge and Michigan Supreme Court justice; his wife, Ann Lapham Graves, was a Battle Creek educator and civic leader; their son, Henry B. Graves, was a Detroit lawyer. Family correspondence concerning life in Battle Creek, Michigan, student life of H. B. Graves at the University of Michigan, 1879-1882, Kansas land speculation, 1883-1885, the Spanish-American War and legal affairs; personal journals and circuit court and Supreme Court record books of B. F. Graves; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. William F. Hopkins (donor no. 4084 ) and came to the library beginning in 1963.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Benjamin F. Graves was born in Rochester, New York on October 18, 1817. In 1837, he commenced the study of law and in 1841 he was admitted to the New York Bar. In 1843, he moved to Battle Creek, Michigan, where he practiced law. In 1857, he was appointed judge of the fifth circuit to fill a vacancy (and also serving for a short time as a member of the Supreme Court under the old system). When his term as appointed judge expired, Graves won election to continue as circuit court judge. He resigned in 1866 because of illness, but in 1867, he won election as Justice of the Supreme Court. He was reelected in 1875 then stepped down in 1884 at the completion of his term
Ann Lapham Graves was a Battle Creek, Michigan educator and civic leader.
Henry B. Graves, the son of Benjamin F. Graves and Ann Lapham Graves, attended the University of Michigan, 1878-1882, later becoming a Detroit attorney.
The Benjamin F. Graves papers consist of family correspondence concerning life in Battle Creek, Michigan, student life of H. B. Graves at the University of Michigan, 1879-1882, Kansas land speculation, 1883-1885, the Spanish-American War and legal affairs; personal journals and circuit court and Michigan Supreme Court record books of B. F. Graves; and correspondence of Henry B. Graves and Ann Lapham Graves. The collection has been arranged by name of individual family member: Benjamin F. Graves; Lapham family; Henry B. Graves; and Miscellaneous.
The correspondence of Benjamin F. Graves includes letters from Henry B. Brown, December 26, 1890; Julius C. Burrows, March 17, 1869; James V. Campbell, 1858-1883; Isaac P. Christiancy, June 1868, November and December 1862, February 1873, August 1877; Thomas M. Cooley (throughout); Donald M. Dickinson, undated and December 1883; Alpheus Felch, December 1894; and John W. Longyear, April 1864 and March 1865.
Subjects:
Battle Creek (Mich.); Calhoun County (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Education--Michigan.; Graves, Benjamin Franklin, b. 1817.; Judges--Michigan.; Kansas.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Republican Party (Mich.); University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Teachers--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Women teachers--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Women--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Graves, Benjamin Franklin, b. 1817.
Contributors:
Brown, Henry Billings, 1836-1913.; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Campbell, James V. (James Valentine), 1823-1890.; Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.; Felch, Alpheus, 1804-1896.; Graves, Ann Lapham, 1822-1894.; Graves, Henry B. (Henry Ballard), 1861-1952.; Bowen, Lydia Graves.; Longyear, John Wesley, 1820-1875.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Benjamin F. Graves
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1848-1859 (Box 1)
    - 1860-1864 (Box 1)
    - 1865-1869 (Box 1)
    - 1870-1872 (Box 1)
    - 1873-1879 (Box 1)
    - 1880-1893 (Box 1)
    - 1894-1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900-1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters to B.F. Graves from wife Ann (Box 1)
  - Letters to B.F. Graves from son Henry (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Will of Benjamin F. Graves (Box 1)
  - Certificates of election (Box 1)
  - Articles and addresses, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning the 1902 reception for Graves by the Detroit bar, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Record of accounts 1896-1902 (Box 1)
  - Journals
    - 1889-1893 (Box 1)
    - 1894-1898 (Box 1)
    - 1899-1901 (Box 1)
    - 1901-1904 (Box 1)
  - Law digests, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Book of Demands 1847 (Box 2)
  - Account book 1847-1849 (also contains draft of speech) (Box 2)
  - Calhoun County Circuit Court Law Journal 1833-1840 (Box 2)
  - Kalamazoo Circuit Court Record Book 1857 (Box 2)
  - Circuit Court Record Book 1861-1862 (Box 2)
  - Circuit Court Record Book 1866 (Box 2)
  - Circuit Court Law Digest (Box 2)
  - Supreme Court minute book 1868 (Box 2)
- Lapham family
  - Lapham family letters 1815, 1843-1847 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Ann (Lapham) Graves from her mother 1847-1868 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Ann (Lapham) Graves from her husband, Benjamin 1853-1884 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Ann (Lapham) Graves from her son, Henry 1867-1897 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Ann Graves correspondence (Box 3)
  - Ann Graves manuscripts (Box 3)
- Henry B. Graves
  - Letters to Henry B. Graves from his father Benjamin 1881-1894 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Henry B. Graves from his mother Ann
    - 1879 (Box 3)
    - 1880 (Box 3)
    - 1881 (Box 3)
    - 1882 (Box 3)
    - 1883 (Box 3)
    - 1884-1885 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Henry B. Graves from his sister Lydia 1875-1894 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Henry B. Graves from his nephew Herbert Bowen 1898 concerning Spanish-American War service (Box 3)
  - Letters to Henry B. Graves from business associates in Kansas 1894-1895 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of H.B. Graves with Judge Clement Smith (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous H.B. Graves correspondence 1928-1950 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - H.B. Graves citations and memorabilia (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous Lydia Graves correspondence 1862-1918 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Photographs -- portraits (Box 3)